Preliminary guide to the Barney Circle interstate bridge fight records, 1979-1996 MS2355
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Barney Circle interstate bridge fight records
1979 - 1996
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Herman, Christopher
MS2355
10.5 Linear Feet
The Citizens Committee to Stop It Again (CCSIA) emerged as a group of neighbors and neighborhoods on both sides of the Anacostia River affected by the traffic movements (congestion, etc.) and loss of parkland amenity that would result from the proposed interstate bridge at the Barney Circle. The CCSIA worked with other community groups and the local chapter of the Sierra Club and showed that the freeway would increase congestion of the freeway and street networks while converting scarce urban riverfront parkland. This collection dcuments include reports, memorandum, correspondence, fliers, testimony and articles that describe the Citizens Committee to Stop It Again in their efforts to stop a proposed interstate bridge at Barney Circle. The records date from 1979 - 1996.
Conditions Governing Access
Collection is open for research.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Christopher Herman 2016 May 6 (2016.067)
Arrangement
The folders are in the original order.
Biographical / Historical
As proposed the bridge would extend the Southeast Freeway through riverfront parkland over a new Anacostia River crossing and linked the Southeast Freeway to the Anacostia Freeway at East Capitol Street. For the opposition a key player was Roberts Owen, the Covington and Burling lawyer who was also active in the Three Sisters Bridge fight decades earlier working with Peter Craig. Owen brought a legal action that helped push the District toward its decision to cancel the project. The project funds were ultimately used for rehabilitation of New York Avenue as well as other uses.
The Citizens Committee to Stop It Again (CCSIA) emerged as a group of neighbors and neighborhoods on both sides of the Anacostia River affected by the traffic movements (congestion, etc.) and loss of parkland amenity. The CCSIA worked with other community groups and the local chapter of the Sierra Club and showed that the freeway would increase congestion of the freeway and street networks while converting scarce urban riverfront parkland.
Scope and Contents
This collection contains records of the group Citizens Committee to Stop It Again (CCSIA). Documents include reports, memorandum, correspondence, fliers, testimony and articles that describe the CCSIA efforts to stop a proposed interstate bridge at Barney Circle. The records date from 1979 through 1996.
Urban transportation; Transportation; Transportation -- Washington Metropolitan Area; Barney Circle (Washington, D.C.); Express highways; Herman, Christopher
- Notes, Undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  General
  File includes handwritten notes on project documents, meetings, and court cases.
- Documents from 1989 [1/4] (Box 1, Folder 2)
  File includes documents from the Barney Circle Freeway Modification Study, correspondences, and meeting minutes of the DOT/FHWA Working Group.
- Documents from 1989 [2/4] (Box 1, Folder 3)
  File includes correspondences with the Department of Transportation of the government of the District of Columbia, Blunt and Evans, consulting engineers and documents regarding Barney Circle Freeway Modification Study Geotechnic Final Technical Report Number Three.
- Documents from 1989 [3/4] (Box 1, Folder 4)
  Contents include meeting minutes from Barney Circle Steering Committee Meetings, memorandums from the SU Department of Transportation Federal Highway Administration, and Barney Circle Freeway Modification Project final environment impact statement re-evaluation form.
- Documents from 1989 [4/4] (Box 1, Folder 5)
  Contents include Anacostia Park from A Historical Archaeological Perspective and correspondences betweening various parties realted to consulting on the project.
- Barney, Blunt and Evans Report [1/2], Undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Barney, Blunt and Evans Report [2/2], Undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Documents [1/2], 1982-1993 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  File contatins correspondeces, meeting minutes, and archaeological reports.
- Documents [2/2], 1982-1993 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  File includes meeting minutes, correspondences, and copies of newspaper articles regarding the project.
- Traffic Analysis, 1993 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- 1988 Public Hearing Report [1/2], 11-12 May 1988 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- 1988 Public Hearing Report [2/2], 11-12 May 1988 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- 1983 Traffic Report [1/2] (Box 2, Folder 7)
- 1983 Traffic Report [2/2] (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Final Environmental Impact Statement [1/3], 1983 (Box 3, Folder 1)
- Final Environmental Impact Statement [2/3], 1983-1993 (Box 3, Folder 2)
- Final Environmental Impact Statement [3/3], 1983 (Box 3, Folder 3)
- Documents [1/2], 1993-1996 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  File includes project correspondences, project research notes, and legal documents.
- Documents [2/2], 1996 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  Files includes project correspondences, legal documents, meeting notes regarding topics like ramps, cemetery noise, etc., and design options.
- Documents [1/3], 1983-1996 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  Files includes documents like the Final Environmental Impact Statement Re-Evaluation Report, Traffic Technical Study notes,and project correspondences.
- Documents [2/3], 1983-1993 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  File includes complilation of most important official reports and audits issued during project.
- Documents [3/3], 1992-1993 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  File includes report on 2010 traffic predictions, copies of news articles, and correspondences.
- Documents from 1993 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  Contents include correspondences with Citizens Committee to Stop It Again, Sharon Pratt Kelly, David Clarke, Covington and Burling, and newspaper articles.
- Documents from 1985 [1/2] (Box 4, Folder 5)
  Contents include correspondences with the US Department of Transportation, US Department of the Interior, Citizens Committee to Stop It Again, and the Congressional Cemetery Association, and hand written notes.
- Documents from 1985 [2/2] (Box 4, Folder 6)
  Contents include Barney Circle Design Study notes, handwritten notes, correspondences with Frank Wolf, the Department of Public Works with the Government of the District of Columbia and the Citizens Committee to Stop It Again.
- Documents from 1988 [1/3] (Box 5, Folder 1)
  File includes project correspondences, meeting minutes, and maps of areas related to the project.
- Documents from 1988 [2/3] (Box 5, Folder 2)
  File includes audio tape and promotional information fliers.
- Documents from 1988 [3/3] (Box 5, Folder 3)
  File includes public hearing comments, research reports, and correspondences.
- Documents from 1987 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  Contents include correspondences with entities such as the Congressional Cemetery Association and the Department of Public Works withthe Government of the District of Columbia.
- Documents from 1986 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  Contents include correspondences with entities such as the US Environmental Protection Agency, Mayor Marion Barry Jr., Citizens Committee to Stop It Again, Congressional Cemetery Association and the Department of Public Works withthe Government of the District of Columbia.
- Documents from 1992 [1/2] (Box 5, Folder 6)
  Contents include correspondences with entities such as the Department of Public Works withthe Government of the District of Columbia, the Citizens Committee to Stop It Again and documents from the Stopping the Barney Circle Interstate meeting agenda and newspaper articles.
- Documents from 1992 [2/2] (Box 5, Folder 7)
  Contents include Barney Circle meeting and correspondences with the Citizens Committee to Stop It Again.
- Documents from 1991 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  Contents include correspondences with the Congressional Cemetery Association, the Citizens Committee to Stop It Again, and meeting notes on the Barney Circle Interstate
- Documents, 1980-1994 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  Contents include project schedule
- Documents from 1983 (original folder title 1983.2) [1/2] (Box 6, Folder 3)
  Contents include correspondence with entities such as the Congressional Cemetery Association, the Department of Transportation of the Government of the District of Columbia, the Department of the Interior, and notes from the Advisory Council on Historic Preservation
- Documents from 1983 (original folder title 1983.2) [2/2] (Box 6, Folder 4)
  Contents include correspondence with entities such as the Department of the Interior and notes from the Advisory Council on Historic Preservation and the National Parks Service.
- Documents from 1983 (original folder title 1983.1) (Box 6, Folder 5)
  Contents include correspondence with the Department of Transportation with the Government of the District of Columbia, the US Department of the Interior, the National Capital Planning Commission, the Congressional Cemetery Association,Environmental Policy Center, the Commission of Fine Arts and governmental memorandums
- Documents from 1982 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  Contents include the Barney Circle Fifth Steering Committee Meeting, meeting minutes for the National Park Service, and correspondences
- Documents from 1981 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  Contents includes correspondences, meeting minutes with Blunt and Evans, consulting engineers.
- Documents from 1980 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  Contents include the District of Columbia Department of Transportation Study of Freeway System Modifications at Barney Circle and Related Actions
- Final Environmental Impact Statement Re-Evaluation Report (Final FEIS Re-Evaluation), 1989-1993 (Box 7, Folder 2)
- Documents from 1984 (original title 1984.2) [1/3] (Box 7, Folder 3)
  Contents include meeting agenda, documents from the Department of Transportation for the United States, correspondences with the Congressional Cemetery Association, and personal memoradum.
- Documents from 1984 (original title 1984.2) [2/3] (Box 7, Folder 4)
  Contents include meeting agendas, documents from the Department of Transportation and the Department of Public Works for the United States, correspondences with the Congressional Cemetery Association, and personal memoradum.
- Documents from 1984 (original title 1984.2) [3/3] (Box 7, Folder 5)
  Contents include meeting agendas, documents from the Department of Transportation and the Department of Public Works for the United States, correspondences and personal memoradums.
- Documents from 1984 (original title 1984.3) [1/3] (Box 7, Folder 6)
  Contents include documents from the Department of Public Works for the United States, the National Park Service, Citizens Committee to Stop It Again correspondences and personal memoradums.
- Documents from 1984 (original title 1984.3) [2/3] (Box 7, Folder 7)
  Contents include documents such as meeting agendas.
- Notes, Undated (Box 8, Folder 1)
  Handwritten log of daily activites regarding the project
- Documents from 1984 (original title 1984.3) [3/3] (Box 8, Folder 2)
  DC Department of Public Works the Regional Truck Network map
- Environmental Literacy Education, 1983-1989 (Box 8, Folder 3)
- Environmental Literacy EducatioDocuments from 1984 (original title 1984.1) [2/2] (Box 8, Folder 4)
  Contents include correspondences, "What is the Barney Circle Project" informational pamphlet, analysis of project.
- Newpapers [1/3], 1990-1993 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  Contents include newspaper articles related to the project.
- Newpapers [2/3], 1985-1990 (Box 8, Folder 6)
- Newpapers [3/3], 1983-1985 (Box 8, Folder 7)
- Press Materials [4/4], Undated (Box 8, Folder 8)
  Contents include newspaper articles and correspondences related to the project.
- Petitions, Undated (Box 8, Folder 9)
- Directories [1/2], Undated (Box 8, Folder 10)
- Documents, 1983-1985 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  Contents include Participant's Course Book and correspondences and Department of the Interior Departmental Manual.
- Documents from 1984 (original title 1984.1) [1/2] (Box 9, Folder 2)
- Project Documents [1/3], 1980-1988 (Box 9, Folder 3)
- Project Documents [2/3], 1980-1988 (Box 9, Folder 4)
- Congressional Cemetery Boundary Description, Undated (Box 9, Folder 5)
- Project Documents [3/3], 1981-1989 (Box 9, Folder 6)
- Court Case Files [1/2], 1991 (Box 10, Folder 1)
- Court Case Files [2/2], 1991 (Box 10, Folder 2)
- Barney Circle Freeway Modification Study: Final Environmental Impact Study volume 1, August 1983 (Box 10, Folder 3)
- Barney Circle Freeway Modification Study: Final Environmental Impact Study volume 2, August 1983 (Box 10, Folder 4)
- Barney Circle Freeway Modification Study: Draft Environmental Impact Statement, February 1983 (Box 10, Folder 5)
- Project Documents, 1983-1988 (Box 10, Folder 6)
- Geotechnic: Final Technical report Number Three, February 1983 (Box 10, Folder 7)
- Court Case Files [1/6], 1983 (Box 11, Folder 1)
- Court Case Files [2/6], 1983 (Box 11, Folder 2)
- Court Case Files [3/6], 1983 (Box 11, Folder 3)
- Court Case Files [4/6], 1981-1982 (Box 11, Folder 4)
- Court Case Files [5/6], 1983 (Box 11, Folder 5)
- Court Case Files [6/6], 1983 (Box 11, Folder 6)
- B.C.: Studies: Blunt and Evans (MOH) 999-5497 volume 1 (original title) [1/3], 16 April 1982 (Box 11, Folder 1)
- B.C.: Studies: Blunt and Evans (MOH) 999-5497 volume 1 (original title) [2/3], 7 December 1981 (Box 11, Folder 2)
- B.C.: Studies: Blunt and Evans (MOH) 999-5497 volume 1 (original title) [3/3], 1981-1994 (Box 11, Folder 3)
- Civil Court Case #94-1051 and #94-1101 volume 58,59,18, 1985 (Box 11, Folder 4)
- Civil Court Cases #94-1051 and #94-1101 volumes 16, 34, 98, 21, 1979-1992 (Box 11, Folder 5)
- Civil Court Cases #94-1051 and #94-1101 volumes 21, 22, 75, 1989-1992 (Box 11, Folder 6)
- B.C.: Studies: Blunt and Evans (MOH) 999-5497 volume 1 (original title) [1/3], 16 April 1982 (Box 12, Folder 1)
- B.C.: Studies: Blunt and Evans (MOH) 999-5497 volume 1 (original title) [2/3], 7 December 1981 (Box 12, Folder 2)
- B.C.: Studies: Blunt and Evans (MOH) 999-5497 volume 1 (original title) [3/3], 1981-1994 (Box 12, Folder 3)
- Civil Court Case #94-1051 and #94-1101 volume 58, 59, 18, 1985 (Box 12, Folder 4)
- Civil Court Case #94-1051 and #94-1101 volume 16, 34, 98, 21, 1979-1992 (Box 12, Folder 5)
- Civil Court Case #94-1051 and #94-1101 volume 21, 22, 75, 1989-1992 (Box 12, Folder 6)
- Civil Court Cases #94-1051 and #94-1101 volume 75, 1980-1984 (Box 13, Folder 1)
- Civil Court Cases #94-1051 and #94-1101 volumes 10, 95, 96, 1984-1994 (Box 13, Folder 2)
- Civil Court Cases #94-1051 and #94-1101 volumes 5, 96, 2, 1981-1994 (Box 13, Folder 3)
- Civil Court Cases #94-1051 and #94-1101 volumes 2, 4, 1981-1982 (Box 13, Folder 4)
- Civil Court Cases #94-1051 and #94-1101 volumes 94, 78, 77, 51, 1983-1993 (Box 13, Folder 5)
- Civil Court Cases #94-1051 and #94-1101 volumes 51, 12, 1985-1994 (Box 14, Folder 1)
- Civil Court Cases #94-1051 and #94-1101 volumes 51, 11, 90, 9, 1983-1993 (Box 14, Folder 2)
- Civil Court Cases #94-1051 and #94-1101 volume 9, 1984-1995 (Box 14, Folder 3)
- Civil Court Cases #94-1051 and #94-1101 volumes 54, 60, 62, 1984-1985 (Box 14, Folder 4)
- Civil Court Cases #94-1051 and #94-1101 volumes 60, 110, 58, 53, 14, 1983-1987 (Box 14, Folder 5)
- Administrative Record volumes 1-98, undated (Box 14, Folder 6)
- Administrative Record Volumes 1-98, Undated (Box 15, Folder 1)
- Civil Court Cases #94-1051 and #94-1101 volume 56, 1984 (Box 15, Folder 2)
- Civil Court Cases #94-1051 and #94-1101 volume 57, 1985 (Box 15, Folder 3)
- Civil Court Cases #94-1051 and #94-1101 master index volumes 99-130, Undated (Box 15, Folder 4)
- Civil Court Cases #94-1051 and #94-1101 volumes 113, 45, 1983-1998 (Box 15, Folder 5)
- Civil Court Cases #94-1051 and #94-1101 volume 45, 46, 1983-1988 (Box 15, Folder 6)
- Civil Court Cases #94-1051 and #94-1101 volume 46, 1983 (Box 15, Folder 7)
- Civil Court Cases #94-1051 and #94-1101 volume 46, 61, 1985 (Box 16, Folder 1)
- 1995 Council Vote (Box 16, Folder 2)
- Ramp, 1995-1996 (Box 16, Folder 3)
- Barton Ascidmon, 1993-1995 (Box 16, Folder 4)
- Incoming Correspondence [1/3], 1994-1995 (Box 16, Folder 5)
- Incoming Correspondence [2/3], 1994-1995 (Box 16, Folder 6)
- Incoming Correspondence [3/3], 1994-1995 (Box 16, Folder 7)
- Incoming Correspondence [1/6], 1996 (Box 17, Folder 1)
- Incoming Correspondence [2/6], 1995-1996 (Box 17, Folder 2)
- Incoming Correspondence [3/6], 1997-1998 (Box 17, Folder 3)
- Incoming Correspondence [4/6], 1996-1998 (Box 17, Folder 4)
- Incoming Correspondence [5/6], 1996-1998 (Box 17, Folder 5)
- Incoming Correspondence [6/6], 1993-1994 (Box 17, Folder 6)
- Incoming correspondence, 1992-1994 (Box 18, Folder 1)
- Notes and Drafts, 1987-1993 (Box 18, Folder 2)
- Maps, 1993 (Box 18, Folder 3)
- Statement of Opposition to B.C. [Barney Circle] [1/2], 1988-1997 (Box 18, Folder 4)
- Statement of Opposition to B.C. [Barney Circle] [2/2], 1983-1996 (Box 18, Folder 5)
- Trade-In, 1987-1997 (Box 18, Folder 6)
- Press Materials [1/2], Undated (Box 18, Folder 7)
- Press Materials ][2/2], Undated (Box 18, Folder 8)
- Press Materials, 1988-1993 (Box 19, Folder 1)
- Petitiions, April 1988 (Box 19, Folder 2)
- Citizens Committee to Stop It Again [CCSIA] [1/3], 1996-1997 (Box 19, Folder 3)
- Citizens Committee to Stop It Again [CCSIA] [2/3], 1994-1996 (Box 19, Folder 4)
- Citizens Committee to Stop It Again [CCSIA] [3/3], 1993-1995 (Box 19, Folder 5)
- 1995 Environmental Assessment, August 1995 (Box 19, Folder 6)
- Directories, Undated (Box 20, Folder 1)
- Anacostia Park [1/2], Undated (Box 20, Folder 2)
- Anacostia Park [2/2], Undated (Box 20, Folder 3)
- 1995 Environmental Assessment, August 1995 (Box 21, Folder 1)
- Law, 1985-1992 (Box 21, Folder 2)
- Stationary, Undated (Box 21, Folder 3)